<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>neuroConstruct: Software for developing biologically realistic 3D neural networks</title>
  </header>
  <body>

  <figure src="images/GranLayerSmall.png" alt="Network model of granule cell layer of cerebellum"/>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>neuroConstruct has been developed in the <a href="http://www.physiol.ucl.ac.uk/research/silver_a/">Silver Lab</a> in the Department of Physiology at
          <a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk">UCL</a>. neuroConstruct has been designed to simplify development of complex networks
          of biologically realistic neurons, i.e. models incorporating dendritic morphologies and realistic cell membrane conductances.
	  It is implemented in Java and generates script files for the <a  href="http://www.neuron.yale.edu/neuron/">NEURON</a> and
	  <a  href="http://www.genesis-sim.org/GENESIS">GENESIS</a> simulators. It uses the latest <a href="http://www.neuroml.org">NeuroML</a> specifications for neuronal
	  information exchange including <a href="http://www.neuroml.org/standards.html">MorphML</a> and <a href="http://www.neuroml.org/standards.html">ChannelML</a>.</p>
    </section>
	
	
	<section>
		<title>** Latest News **</title>
		<p>The latest version of neuroConstruct is available for download <a href="download/index.html">here</a>.</p> 
		<p>There is a mailing list for neuroConstruct related news. Sign up <a href="http://www.mailinglists.ucl.ac.uk/mailman/listinfo/neuroconstruct">here</a>. </p> 
  	</section>	

    <section>
      <title>What is neuroConstruct?</title>
      <p>Some of the key features of neuroConstruct are:</p>
<ul>
	<li>neuroConstruct can <a href="examples/index.html#morph">import</a> morphology files in GENESIS, NEURON, Neurolucida, SWC and MorphML format for inclusion in network models</li>
      <li>Creation of networks of conductance based neurons, <a href="examples/index.html#packing">positioned in 3D</a></li>
<li>Complex <a href="examples/index.html#conn">connectivity patterns</a> between cell groups can be specified for the networks</li>
<li>Simulations can be run on the <a href="examples/index.html#neuorgen">NEURON or GENESIS</a> platforms</li>
<li>Electrophysiological cellular mechanisms (synapses/channel mechanisms) can be imported from native script files (*.mod or *.g) or created from templates using <a href="examples/index.html#channelml">ChannelML</a></li>
<li>Automatic generation of code to record simulation data and <a href="examples/index.html#analysis">
    visualisation/analysis</a> of data in neuroConstruct</li>

<li>Recorded simulation runs can be viewed and managed through the <a href="examples/index.html#simbrowser">Simulation Browser</a> interface</li>


 </ul>
    </section>
        <section>
      <title>What isn't neuroConstruct?</title>

     <ul>
<li>neuroConstruct is not a replacement for neural network simulators like NEURON or GENESIS</li>
</ul>
<p>These packages have sophisticated environments for creating neuronal simulations from scratch,
and controlling all aspects of the simulation run. neuroConstruct automates the generation of script files for these platforms, and provides
a framework for creating conductance based neuronal models, creating, visualising and analysing networks of cells in 3D, managing simualtions and analysing network firing behaviour.</p>
  </section>

      <section>
      <title>Presentations</title>

<p>The application was presented at the <a
 href="http://www.neuron.yale.edu/neuron/nsm2004/events.html">2004
NEURON Simulator Meeting</a> at Northwestern University in May 2004. A tutorial "Building 3D Network Models with neuroConstruct" was given at the
<a href="http://wam-bamm.org/">World Association of Modelers, First Annual Biologically Accurate Modeling Meeting</a> in March 2005.
A poster entitled "Simulation of Synaptic Integration in Biologically Realistic 3D Neuronal Networks" has been presented at <a href="http://web.sfn.org/am2005/">Neuroscience 2005</a>.
There was a poster presentation on the latest developments with neuroConstruct at <a href="http://www.cnsorg.org/cns_meeting.htm">CNS*2006</a> in Edinburgh.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>

  </section>

  </body>
</document>
