<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>neuroConstruct: Software for developing biologically realistic 3D neural networks</title>
  </header>
  <body>
      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/nature07604.html" 
title="Recent Nature paper using neuroConstruct to investigate gain control in detailed cell models">
  <img src="images/KoleCell.png" 
        alt="Recent Nature paper using neuroConstruct to investigate gain control in detailed cell models"/></a>
        &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/bookdescription.cws_home/713686/description" 
title="Computational Neuroscience in Epilepsy, 2008, I. Soltesz, and K. Staley, eds. (Elsevier). Contains chapter on neuroConstruct.">
  <img src="images/EpilepsyBookCover.PNG" 
        alt="Computational Neuroscience in Epilepsy, 2008, I. Soltesz, and K. Staley, eds. (Elsevier). Contains chapter on neuroConstruct."/></a></p>

      <p>&nbsp;</p>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>neuroConstruct has been developed in the <a href="http://www.physiol.ucl.ac.uk/research/silver_a/">Silver Lab</a> in the Department of Physiology at
          <a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk">UCL</a>. neuroConstruct has been designed to simplify development of complex networks
          of biologically realistic neurons, i.e. models incorporating dendritic morphologies and realistic cell membrane conductances.
      It is implemented in Java and generates script files for the <a  href="docs/Glossary_gen.html#NEURON">NEURON</a> and
      <a  href="docs/Glossary_gen.html#GENESIS">GENESIS</a> simulators. It uses the latest <a href="docs/Glossary_gen.html#NeuroML">NeuroML</a> specifications,
      including <a href="docs/Glossary_gen.html#MorphML">MorphML</a>, <a href="docs/Glossary_gen.html#ChannelML">ChannelML</a> and <a href="docs/Glossary_gen.html#NetworkML">NetworkML</a>.</p>
    </section>


    <section>
        <title>Latest News</title>
        <p>A recent Nature paper (<em>Jason S. Rothman, Laurence Cathala, Volker Steuber, R. Angus Silver, 
        Synaptic depression enables neuronal gain control. Nature 2009</em>) has used neuroConstruct to investigate 
        a detailed layer 5 pyramidal cell model (Kole et al 2008) with dendritically distributed excitatory and 
        inhibitory synaptic input to look at the effects of short term plasticity on gain control (Download: <a  href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/nature07604.html">paper</a>; 
        <a  href="models/index.html#RothmanEtAl_KoleEtAl_PyrCell-N10162">neuroConstruct project</a>). </p>

 
        <p>The latest version of neuroConstruct (<strong>v1.2.0, Dec 2008</strong>) is available for download <a href="download/index.html">here</a>.</p>
        <p>The paper describing the application has been published: <em>
            P. Gleeson, V. Steuber and R. A. Silver, neuroConstruct: A Tool for Modeling Networks of Neurons in 3D Space, Neuron,
            Volume 54, Issue 2, 19 April 2007, Pages 219-235.</em>
            It is available via Open Access <a href="http://www.neuron.org/content/article/abstract?uid=PIIS0896627307002486">here</a>.</p>

            <p>A more complete list of <strong>publications</strong> dealing with neuroConstruct and NeuroML can be found <a href="links/publications.html">here</a>.</p>


        <p>There is a <strong>mailing list</strong> for neuroConstruct related news (<strong>neuroconstruct@ucl.ac.uk</strong>). Sign up <a href="http://www.mailinglists.ucl.ac.uk/mailman/listinfo/neuroconstruct">here</a>. </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What is neuroConstruct?</title>
      
      <p>Some of the key features of neuroConstruct are:</p>
<ul>
    <li>neuroConstruct can <a href="samples/index.html#Ex3_Morphology">import</a> morphology files in GENESIS, NEURON, Neurolucida, SWC and MorphML format for inclusion in single cell or network models, or more abstract cells can also be built manually.</li>
      <li>Creation of networks of conductance based neurons <a href="samples/index.html#Ex2_Packing">positioned in 3D</a></li>
<li>Complex <a href="samples/index.html#Ex5_Networks">connectivity patterns</a> between cell groups can be specified for the networks </li>
<li>Simulations can be run on the <a href="samples/index.html#Ex4_HHCell">NEURON or GENESIS</a> platforms</li>
<li>Biophysically realistic cellular mechanisms (synapses/channel mechanisms) can be imported from native script files (*.mod or *.g) or created from templates using ChannelML</li>
<li>Automatic generation of code to record simulation data and visualisation/analysis of data in neuroConstruct</li>

<li>Recorded simulation runs can be viewed and managed through the Simulation Browser interface</li>


 </ul>
    </section>
        <section>
      <title>What isn't neuroConstruct?</title>

     <ul>
<li>neuroConstruct is not a replacement for neural network simulators like NEURON or GENESIS</li>
</ul>
<p>These packages have sophisticated environments for creating neuronal simulations from scratch,
and controlling all aspects of the simulation run. neuroConstruct automates the generation of script files for these platforms, and provides
a framework for creating conductance based neuronal models, creating, visualising and analysing networks of cells in 3D, managing simualtions and analysing network firing behaviour.</p>


<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

  </section>





  </body>
</document>
