<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>neuroConstruct and NeuroML related publications</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
  
<table class="noborder">

	<tr>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Padraig Gleeson, Volker Steuber, R. Angus Silver</strong></p>
			<p><em>neuroConstruct: A Tool for Modeling Networks of Neurons in 3D Space, Neuron, 
            Volume 54, Issue 2, 19 April 2007, Pages 219-235.</em></p>
		<p><a  href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17442244">PubMed</a>
                        <a href="http://www.neuron.org/content/article/abstract?uid=PIIS0896627307002486">Open access download</a></p>
		</td>
		<td><p>&nbsp;</p>
			The main neuroConstruct paper. An introduction to all of the key functionality, including some 
                        network examples.
		</td>
	</tr>
        
	<tr>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Padraig Gleeson, Volker Steuber, R. Angus Silver</strong></p>
			<p><em>Using neuroConstruct to Develop and Modify Biologically Detailed 3D Neuronal Network Models in Health and Disease. In Computational Neuroscience in Epilepsy, 2008, I. Soltesz, and K. Staley, eds. (Elsevier).
</em></p>
		<p><a href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/bookdescription.cws_home/713686/description">Elsevier</a></p>
		</td>
		<td><p>&nbsp;</p>
			A chapter in a book outlining the various modelling approached being used in epilepsy research. Attractive image on the cover...
                       
		</td>
	</tr>
        
        
	<tr>
		<td>
			<p><strong>
                    Sharon Crook, Padraig Gleeson, Fred Howell, Joe Svitak, R. Angus Silver</strong></p>
			<p><em>MorphML: Level 1 of the NeuroML Standards for Neuronal Morphology Data and Model Specification, 
                        Neuroinformatics 2007, Volume 5; Number 2, Pages 96-104</em></p>
		<p><a  href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17873371">PubMed</a></p>
                </td>
		<td><p>&nbsp;</p>
			The introductory paper to MorphML. Compares morphological representations from 
                        NEURON, GENESIS, Neurolucida and neuroConstruct to MorphML.
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Nigel Goddard, Michael Hucka, Fred Howell, Hugo Cornelis, Kavita Shankar, David Beeman</strong></p>
			<p><em>Towards NeuroML: Model Description Methods for Collaborative Modelling in Neuroscience. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci 356, 1209-1228.</em></p>
		<p><a  href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11545699">PubMed</a></p>
                </td>
		<td><p>&nbsp;</p>
			The original NeuroML introductory paper. Although the actual standards themselves have evolved since this paper
                        (with a focus now on key elements which need to be transferred between neuroinformatics applications, as represented by
                        MorphML, ChannelML and NeuroML, the latest version of which are available <a  href="http://www.morphml.org:8080/NeuroMLValidator/">here</a>) the key aims of NeuroML as outlined in this paper, including clarity, portability and modularity of neuronal model descriptions, remain the same.
                        
		</td>
	</tr>
        
        
	<tr>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Robert C. Cannon, Marc-Oliver Gewaltig, Padraig Gleeson, Upinder S. Bhalla, Hugo Cornelis, Michael L. Hines, 
                        Fredrick W. Howell, Eilif Muller, Joel R. Stiles, Stefan Wils, Erik De Schutter</strong></p>
			<p><em>Interoperability of Neuroscience Modeling Software: Current Status and Future Directions. Neuroinformatics 5, 127-138.</em></p>
		<p><a  href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17873374">PubMed</a></p>
                </td>
		<td><p>&nbsp;</p>
			A review of the current state of interoperability for modelling applications, resulting from a workshop at CNS 2006.
                        
		</td>
	</tr>
        


</table>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
  </body>
</document>
