<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Interacting with native simulators on various platforms</title>
  </header>
  <body>

  <p>Outlined here are some points regarding how neuroConstruct deals with the native simulators on
  various operating systems</p>


    <section>
      <title>General points</title>

<p>neuroConstruct is written in <a href="http://java.sun.com/">Java</a> and so can be used on any platform with a Java Virtual Machine
    together with an implementation of Java3D.</p>
<p>In general, NEURON and/or GENESIS should be present on the same machine as neuroConstruct. The scripts for the target platform 
    are generated based on the network created by neuroConstruct, and these are set running in separate processes via the 
    Java <strong>Runtime.exec()</strong> command.</p>
<p></p>


</section>

<section>
  <title>Linux</title>

  <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>NEURON</strong></p>

  <p>NEURON hoc and mod files are generated from the network model in neuroConstruct. First, the mod files are compiled using
  <strong>nrnivmodl</strong>. This executable is found using the value for the NEURON home directory in <strong>Settings -> 
      General Properties</strong>.
  </p>
  <p>Once the native machine libraries for the channels are generated, the main hoc file is run with <strong>nrngui</strong>. Note that 
      this is   executed in a console window (by prefixing the command with <strong>gnome-terminal -x</strong> (Gnome desktop) or 
      <strong>konsole</strong> (KDE), also set via <strong>Settings -> General Properties</strong>)</p>

  <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>GENESIS</strong></p>
  <p>GENESIS script is generated from the network model and the main file can be run straight away. The <strong>genesis</strong> command,
  together with the name of the main file are executed via <strong>Runtime.exec()</strong>, therefore the location of this executable
  should be in the PATH variable. The command is executed in a new console window as above.</p>


</section>


<section>
  <title>Windows</title>

  <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>NEURON</strong></p>

  <p>NEURON hoc and mod files are generated from the network model in neuroConstruct. First, the mod files are compiled using a command of the form
  <strong>C:\nrn60\bin\rxvt.exe -e C:\nrn60\bin\sh C:\nrn60\lib\mknrndll.sh C:\nrn60</strong>. The <strong>C:\nrn60</strong> is found using the 
          value for the NEURON home directory in <strong>Settings -> General Properties</strong>.
  </p>
  <p>Once the native machine libraries for the channels are generated, the main hoc file is run with <strong>neuron.exe</strong>.</p>

  <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>GENESIS</strong></p>
  <p>GENESIS was for many years not available on Windows. A <a href="http://www.genesis-sim.org/GENESIS/genesis-cygwin/">port</a> has 
      recently been created, which while slower than under Linux, can be used to test generated GENESIS code under Windows. The 
      following assumes Cygwin has been installed at <strong>C:\cygwin</strong> and GENESIS installed at <strong>/usr/local/genesis</strong> i.e.
  <strong>C:\cygwin\usr\local\genesis</strong>.</p>
  <p>
  GENESIS script is generated from the network model and the main file can be run straight away without further compilation.
  The file <strong>{NEUROCONSTRUCT_HOME}/templates/genesisUtils/startxwin2.bat</strong> is used to launch the genesis executable. 
  This is a slightly modified version
  of the <strong>startxwin.bat</strong> supplied with Cygwin for running an XTerm. This mechanism is a bit flaky (e.g. it doesn't 
  like NEURON running under Cygwin at the same time). Please report any problems/solutions to bugs - at - neuroConstruct.org</p>

</section>


<section>
  <title>Mac</title>

<p>neuroConstruct and its 3D visualisation capability has been successfully tested on the Mac, but the interaction with simulation platforms needs more testing.
	NEURON interaction is fine if the Developer Tools (XCode) are installed. Basic GENESIS interaction has been tried successfully too. </p>
<p>If you are interested in helping test the application on this platform, please <a  href="../contact/index.html" >get in touch</a></p>
</section>



<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

  </body>
</document>
