<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Support for NeuroML</title>
  </header>
  <body>
      
  <p>Listed here are all the possible ways neuroConstruct can import/export data in <a href="Glossary_gen.html#NeuroML">NeuroML</a> format</p>


<section>
      <title>ChannelML</title>
      
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to the <strong>Cell Mechanisms</strong> tab, press <strong>Create ChannelML Mechanism</strong> and select the file containing the ChannelML description
(you can find a mapping for NEURON and GENESIS under templates/xmlTemplates/schemata/vx.x/Level2 in the local folder of NeuroConstruct).</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export Network -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Generate all NeuroML scripts</strong>,
 a file for each cell mechanism is also saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project (NOTE: a ChannelML file will be also saved by deafult in each folder of the cellMechanisms folder of the current project).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

</section>


<section>
      <title>MorphML and Morphology</title>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Level 1 = </strong> the anatomy of the cell (pure MorphML description)</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Cell Types</strong> press <strong>Add new Cell Type to project...</strong> and select <strong>NeuroMLConverter</strong> in the scroll down menu.</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export Network -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Export all Cell Types</strong> with the <strong>Level 1</strong> button selected,
 a file for each cell type will be saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Level 2 = </strong> Level 1 and cell biophysics</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Cell Types</strong> tab press <strong>Add new Cell Type to project...</strong> and select <strong>NeuroMLConverter</strong> in the scroll down menu (NOTE: biophysics information is lost).</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export Network -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Export all Cell Types</strong> with the <strong>Level 2</strong> button selected,
 a file for each cell type will be saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Level 3 = </strong> Level 1, Level 2 and network aspects</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Cell Types</strong> press <strong>Add new Cell Type to project...</strong> and select <strong>NeuroMLConverter</strong> in the scroll down menu (NOTE: biophysics and network informations are lost).</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export Network -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Export all Cell Types</strong> with the <strong>Level 3</strong> button selected,
 a file for each cell type will be saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>
<p>or go to <strong>Export Network -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Generate all NeruoML scripts</strong>, a Level 3 description of each cell type will be saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>
</li>
</ul>

</section>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

<section>
      <title>NetworkML</title>

<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to the <strong>Generate</strong> tab, press <strong>Load NetworkML</strong> and select the .xml file containing the NetworklML description</p>
<p>or select <strong>File -> Load NeuroML level 1, 2, 3...</strong> from the main menu and select the .xml file.</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to the <strong>Generate</strong> tab, press <strong>Save NetworkML</strong>,
a NetworkML description of the generated network will be saved in the <strong>savedNetworks</strong> folder of the current project.</p>
<p>or go to <strong>Export Network -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Generate all NeuroML scripts</strong>, a NetworkML description of the generated network will be saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>

</section>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

<section>
      <title>Level 3 NeuroML</title>

<p> NeuroConstruct is able to generate and import a single file containing all the generated elements of a project (cells, mechanisms, inputs, connections, etc).
This file is fully NeuroML compliant and allow easy exchange of self-sufficient models between neuroConstruct users.</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> select <strong>File -> Load NeuroML level 1, 2, 3...</strong> from the main menu and select the Level 3 file to be imported. (NOTE: this could overwrite some existing elements to avoid conflicts)</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export Network -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Generate all NeuroML scripts</strong> with the <strong>Generate single NeuroML Level 3 file</strong> box ticked,
a single file containing all the generated elements will be saved in the <strong>savedNetworks</strong> folder of the current project. (tick the <strong>Add neuroConstruct annotations</strong> box if you wish to include the neuroConstruct specific settings like cell groups, regions, simulation configurations etc)</p>

</section>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

  </body>
</document>
