<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Support for NeuroML in neuroConstruct</title>
  </header>
  <body>
      
  <p>Listed here are all the possible ways neuroConstruct can import/export data in <a href="Glossary_gen.html#NeuroML">NeuroML</a> format</p>



<section>
      <title>Cell morphologies (Levels 1-3)</title>

      <p>neuroConstruct uses an internal data model for cells which is closely linked to <a href="Glossary_gen.html#MorphML">MorphML</a>. See
      <a href="Glossary_gen.html#Morphology save format">here</a> for more details.</p>

      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Level 1: </strong> only the anatomy of the cell (<a href="Glossary_gen.html#MorphML">MorphML</a> description)</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Cell Types</strong> press <strong>Add new Cell Type to project...</strong> and select <strong>NeuroMLConverter</strong> in the scroll down menu.</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Export all Cell Types</strong> with the <strong>Level 1</strong> button selected,
 a file for each cell type will be saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>

      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Level 2:</strong> Level 1 plus cell biophysics (passivel electrical properties and channel placement)</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Cell Types</strong> tab press <strong>Add new Cell Type to project...</strong> and select <strong>NeuroMLConverter</strong> in the scroll down menu.
Note that there should be channel mechanisms present in the project with names corresponding to those in the <strong>&lt;biophysics&gt;</strong> element of the file.</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Export all Cell Types</strong> with the <strong>Level 2</strong> button selected,
 a file for each cell type will be saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>

      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Level 3:</strong> Level 2 plus network aspects (allowed locations of synapse types)</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Cell Types</strong> press <strong>Add new Cell Type to project...</strong> and select <strong>NeuroMLConverter</strong> in the scroll down menu.
Note that there should be channel and synaptic mechanisms present in the project with names corresponding to those in the <strong>&lt;biophysics&gt;</strong> and <strong>&lt;connectivity&gt;</strong> elements of the file.</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Export all Cell Types</strong> with the <strong>Level 3</strong> button selected,
 a file for each cell type will be saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>




<p>&nbsp;</p>
</section>


<section>
      <title>ChannelML</title>

      <p><a href="Glossary_gen.html#ChannelML">ChannelML</a> files can be used for <a href="Glossary_gen.html#Cell Mechanism">Cell Mechanisms</a> in neuroConstruct. They can be used for channels
      (e.g. Na<sup>+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup> distributed ion channels), synapses (fixed and plastic chemical synaptic mechanisms), gap junctions, ion concentrations (e.g. pool of internal 
      Ca<sup>2+</sup>) and point processes (e.g. simple integrate and fire mechanisms). The ChannelML file, a number of XSL mappings to simulators and a properties.xml file are stored for
      each cell mechanism in the <strong>cellMechanism</strong> folder of a neuroConstruct project. Details of the process to convert an existing channel script, e.g. a mod file, to ChannelML
      is outlined <a  href="importneuron.html#Converting+mod+file%2FGENESIS+script+channels+into+ChannelML" >here</a>
      </p>

      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> to use a <a href="Glossary_gen.html#ChannelML">ChannelML</a> based cell mechanism in neuroConstruct, ensure the file only contains a single 
<strong>&lt;channel_type&gt;</strong> element, go to the <strong>Cell Mechanisms</strong> tab, press <strong>Create ChannelML Mechanism</strong>, name the new mechanism
 and select the file containing the ChannelML description. XSL mappings for
NEURON and GENESIS can be found under templates/xmlTemplates/Schemata/vx.x.x/Level2 in the local folder of neuroConstruct. Alternatively, a small number of example ChannelML
mechanisms can be imported (and altered afterwards) by pressing <strong>Add ChannelML from Template</strong>.</p>

      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Generate all NeuroML scripts</strong>,
 a file for each ChannelML based cell mechanism is saved in the <strong>generatedNeuroML</strong> folder of the current project.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

</section>


<section>
      <title>NetworkML</title>
      <p><a href="Glossary_gen.html#NetworkML">NetworkML</a> files can be saved and reloaded in neuroConstruct in either XML or <a href="Glossary_gen.html#HDF5">HDF5</a> formats.</p>
      <p>The NetworkML files read by neuroConstruct can come from any application which generates valid NetworkML, but nothe that the cell group 
      and cell type names used in the <strong>&lt;populations&gt;</strong> element, and the network connection names used in the <strong>&lt;projections&gt;</strong>
      element must match the names of these already present in the project. </p>
      <p>Included with neuroConstruct are a number of <a href="Glossary_gen.html#Python">Python</a>
      scripts, and these allow reading/writing of NetworkML (in the <strong>pythonNeuroML/Examples</strong> folder in the install directory) and interaction with 
      neuroConstruct through <a href="http://www.jython.org/">Jython</a> to generate a network which can then be saved as NetworkML (e.g. <strong>Ex4_SaveNetworkML.py</strong> 
      in the <strong>pythonnC</strong> folder in the install directory). More details can be found <a href="python.html">here</a>.</p>

      

      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> go to the <strong>Generate</strong> tab, press <strong>Load NetworkML</strong> and select the XML or HDF5 file containing the NetworkML description.
</p>

      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to the <strong>Generate</strong> tab, press <strong>Save NetworkML</strong>,
a NetworkML description of the generated network will be saved in the <strong>savedNetworks</strong> folder of the current project.</p>
</section>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

<section>
      <title>Level 3 NeuroML</title>

<p>neuroConstruct is able to generate and import and export <em>single files</em> containing all the model elements covered from Levels 1-3.
This file is fully NeuroML compliant and allow easy exchange of self-sufficient models between neuroConstruct users.</p>
      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>IMPORT:</strong> select <strong>File -> Import NeuroML Levels 1, 2, 3...</strong> from the main menu and
select the Level 3 file to be imported. If the file contains elements (e.g. cell types) with the same names as are used
in the project, warnings will be shown. It is possible to import a Level 3 file into a new, empty project (or select <strong>Import NeuroML Levels 1, 2, 3...</strong>
when no project is open) and neuroConstruct specific entities (e.g. 3D Regions) will be created to accomodate the elements in the file.</p>
      <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>EXPORT:</strong> go to <strong>Export -> NeuroML</strong> tab and press <strong>Generate all NeuroML scripts</strong> with the <strong>Generate single NeuroML Level 3 file</strong> box ticked,
a single file containing all the generated elements will be saved in the <strong>savedNetworks</strong> folder of
the current project. Tick the <strong>Add neuroConstruct annotations</strong> box if you wish to include the neuroConstruct
specific settings like regions, simulation configurations etc. This will still produce a valid NeuroML Level 3 file (other
applications can ignore these annotations), but this will facilitate importing the model in the file into a new neuroConstruct project.</p>

</section>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

  </body>
</document>
