<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Simulation Configurations</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
  
  
    

<p>Most neuroConstruct <a href="Glossary_gen.html#Project">Projects</a> will illustrate not just a single aspect of a cell
    or network, but will seek to show how the cells react under different inputs, or how a network behaves
    with different <a href="Glossary_gen.html#Cell Group">Cell Groups</a>/cell populations present, etc. A particular Simulation
                 Configuration has a number of Cell Groups, Network Connections, Electrical Inputs, and Plots 
                 associated with it, along with a simulation duration. </p>

<p>One of these configurations must be specified
                 when the network is generated, indicating which of the aspects of the model is to be simulated. A Default
                 Simulation Configuration is always present, and if there is only this one, all new Cell Groups, etc. will be
                 automatically associated with it; otherwise new Cell Groups, Network Connections, etc. have to be manually added to 
                 whichever particular Simulation Configuration they are required for.  </p>
             
             
<p>Ideally there will be one Simulation Configuration associated with the project for each aspect being illustrated by the model as 
    a whole. If the model is accompanied by a paper, this could translate to one Simulation Configuration for each figure. If a published 
    model is being reproduced in neuroConstruct, it would be a useful goal to include Simulation Configurations reproducing the figures
    of the paper as closely as possible. New  Simulation Configurations can also be added to test new features of the network. Having a number 
    of 'working'  Simulation Configurations is useful when a model is being developed, as following changes in the cells/cell mechanisms, the 
    older Simulation Configurations can be tested to ensure they are still producing the desired results.</p>
          
                 

  </body>
</document>
