<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Tutorial of basic neuroConstruct functionality</title>
  </header>
  <body>



      <section>
      <title>Set up project and add cell</title>

      <p><a  href="../install.html#Building+and+running" >Run</a> neuroConstruct. Click on <strong>File -> New Project</strong></p>

      <p>Enter the <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#Project">project</a> name and the directory in which to place
          the main project folder. Click <strong>OK</strong></p>


      <p>Ignore the offer to create a few sample objects in the new project. That would be too easy.</p>


      <p>Add a <a  href="../Glossary_gen.html#Cell Type">Cell Type</a>. Select the tab <strong>Cell Types</strong> and
press <strong>Add New Cell Type to Project</strong>.

Add a SimpleCell to the project (select in drop down menu), naming it Simple. <a  href="../celltypes.html">More on Cell Types</a></p>


<p>Now press the <strong>View/edit morphology</strong> button below the panel giving details on the cell. This will change to the <strong>Visualisation</strong> tab and display the cell in 3D. For
    various tips on what's possible when the cell is displayed in 3D see <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#3D View of Cells">here</a>.</p>

</section>

<section>
      <title>Add channel mechanism</title>

      <p>There is a morphologically reasonable cell in the project now, but there is something missing. Click on the <strong>Validate</strong> button below the main menu.
          This signals the fact that there are no cell density mechanisms present. A cell needs these for simulation of realistic electrophysiological behaviour. Other project or cell specific errors
      will appear here as they occur.</p>

      <p>First a cell mechanism will be added to the project. Go to tab <strong>Cell Mechanisms</strong>. Click <strong>Add ChannelML from Template</strong>. This presents a list
    of <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#Channel Mechanism">Channel Mechanisms</a> and <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#Synaptic Mechanism">Synaptic Mechanisms</a> whose parameters are
    specified in <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#ChannelML">ChannelML</a> that serve as templates for your own channels/synapses. Select <strong>Leak Conductance</strong>, which represents
a passive conductance on the membrane of the cell, i.e. current will leak out/in to the cell if its membrane potential is different from the reversal potential of this channel. Press <strong>OK</strong>
and accept the name of the cell mechanism. You are presented with a summary of the parameters of the mechanism. Select the second tab <strong>ChannelML file</strong> to see what's actually in the XML file.
Note: it is also possible to use a cell mechanism based on a NMODL file or GENESIS channel script. See <a href="../importneuron.html">here</a> for an outline of the process</p>

<p>Close this and return to <strong>Visualisation</strong>. Select the cell name in the drop down box and press <strong>View</strong>. Select <strong>Cell density mechanisms</strong> in the lower right drop
down box and press <strong>Edit density mechanisms</strong>. Under <strong>Cell Mechanisms</strong> select the mechanism you've just added. Select <strong>all</strong> and press the right arrow to indicate this mechanism is
present on all sections. Accept the default value for maximum conductance density. Press <strong>OK</strong>. Now click <strong>Validate</strong> again and you'll see that the cell meets the minimum requirements for
use in a simulation.</p>

</section>

<section>
      <title>Packing in 3D</title>

      <p>Now we need to specify a <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#Region">Region</a> in which to place the cells. Go to the tab
          <strong>Regions</strong>, select <strong>Add New Region</strong>. Accept the defaults and press <strong>OK</strong>.</p>


      <p>Go to the tab <strong>Cell Groups</strong> and click <strong>New Cell Group</strong>. This results in a dialog to
specify the name, Cell Type (here the only choice is Simple),
which Region the cells will be placed in, the colour, and the <a  href="../Glossary_gen.html#Packing Pattern">packing pattern</a>.
Press the <strong>Choose...</strong> button next to Packing Pattern. In the field for Cell Number, enter the number
of cells you want randomly placed in the Region.</p>

<p>A dialog box will ask if you wish to record the membrane potential of the cell during simulations. Press <strong>Yes</strong>. It would be good to also view the membrane potential while the simulation is running.
    Go to tab <strong>Input/Output</strong>. Click on the entry for saving the voltage in the lower table and click <strong>Edit selected plot</strong>. This dialog specified what variable to save and/or plot during a simulation,
    which cells of the Cell Group to record, etc. In the bottom drop down box select <strong>Plot and save</strong>. Press <strong>OK</strong>.
</p>

<p>A stimulation must be applied to the cell or it will be an uninteresting simulation. Still at tab <strong>Input/Output</strong>,
    select <strong>Add electrophysiological input</strong>. Keep the default values (a single current pulse on the soma of all cells in the Cell Group) and press <strong>Ok</strong>.</p>


<p>Select the tab <strong>Generate</strong>. Press the <strong>Generate Cell Positions and Connections</strong> button.</p>

<p>Go to <strong>Visualisation</strong>. In the drop down box, select <em>Latest Generated Positions</em>.
    Press <strong>View</strong>.</p>

</section>

<section>
      <title>Running/replaying simulation</title>

      <p>If <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#NEURON">NEURON</a> or <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#GENESIS">GENESIS</a> are installed (assuming NEURON) go to tab
<strong>Export</strong> and select the <strong>NEURON</strong> tab.
Select the <strong>Show 3D potential plot</strong> checkbox, and click <strong>Create hoc simulation</strong>. This will create the hoc code
for the main file, and a template for the cell, as well as <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#NMODL">NMODL</a> code for the channels. The NMODL files
will be compiled and a confirmation shown.
</p>

<p>Click on <strong>Run Simulation</strong>. This should start NEURON and run the simulation you have just created.
    If there is a problem starting, and it is installed correctly go to <strong>Settings -> General Properties</strong> and check the entries there.</p>

<p>Back in neuroConstruct, once the simulation has finished, go to tab <strong>Visualisation</strong>, and click on <strong>Previous Simulations</strong>
You will see a list of all recorded simulations. Click on the simulation just completed and click <strong>Load Simulation</strong>.
The generated cell appears again. Press <strong>Replay</strong> to view the recorded simulation.
</p>
<p>Select the Cell Group and Cell Number in the drop down boxes followed by <strong>Plot selected</strong>. This shows the recorded
voltage trace. Individual cells can also be selected by clicking on them in the 3D view. Note however, if the cell is inside a transparent
3D Region or if there are other cells close by it may be difficult to select the correct object. Click <strong>3D Settings</strong> and deselect displaying of Regions</p>


</section>

<section>
      <title>Further things to try...</title>


      <p>Change the layout of the cells generated. In tab <strong>Cell Groups</strong>, click the table entry under
          <strong>Cell Packing Adapter</strong>. This will open up the packing pattern dialog. If the random packing adapter is selected,
          the number of cells to pack into the Region can be changed. There are also options to change settings on whether the cell bodies
          can overlap, and whether the whole cell body should stay inside the region, or just the centres. The packing pattern itself can be changed too,
          from randomly placed to a single cell placed at a precise 3D point, a hexagonal pattern, cubic close packed, etc.
          More on the various types of <a  href="../Glossary_gen.html#Packing Pattern">packing patterns available</a>.</p>


      <p>Change the size/shape of the Region. Go to tab <strong>Region</strong>, select the line with the Region details,
        click on <strong>Edit Selected Region</strong>, and either change the position and size of the Rectangular region
        or change it to a Spherical Region placed in 3D.</p>

       <p>Edit the morphology of the cell. Go to tab <strong>Visualisation</strong>, select <strong>3D Settings</strong> and make sure display is on <strong>All solid</strong>
           and the 3D axes are not shown. Save these settings and view the cell you've added. Click on any of the segments. Make sure <strong>Pick Segments/Sections</strong> is selected
           in the lower right drop down box. It will turn red (if there are any other segments in the same section they will turn yellow). Click on <strong>Edit...</strong> and you can alter the end points, etc.
           At the drop down box in the Segment selector, there are a number of functions for adding new segments, specifying axonal arbours for <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#Volume Based Connection">Volume Based Connections</a>, etc.</p>


    <p>Add some other Cell Mechanisms to the project (e.g. <strong>NaConductance</strong>, <strong>KConductance</strong>) and apply these to the cell membrane in the same way as the leak conductance.</p>


</section>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
  </body>
</document>
