<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Very quick tutorial</title>
  </header>
  <body>





<p>The quickest way to create a simulation in in neuroConstruct is as follows:</p>
<ol>

<li><a  href="../install.html#Building+and+running" >Run</a> neuroConstruct. Click on <strong>File -> New Project</strong></li>

<li>Enter the project name and the directory in which to place the main project folder. Click <strong>OK</strong></li>

<li>Accept the offer to create a few sample objects in the new project.</li>


<li>Select the tab <strong>Generate</strong>. Press the <strong>Generate Cell Positions and Connections</strong> button.</li>


<li>Go to <strong>Visualisation</strong>. In the drop down box, select <em>Latest Generated Positions</em>.
Press <strong>View</strong>. You should see an abstract neuron placed in a 3D box. There will also be a pipette like structure
signifying an electrical input.</li>


<li>If <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#NEURON">NEURON</a> or <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#GENESIS">GENESIS</a> are installed (assuming NEURON) go to tab
<strong>Export</strong> and select the <strong>NEURON</strong> tab.
Select the <strong>Show 3D potential plot</strong> checkbox, and click <strong>Create hoc simulation</strong>. This will create the hoc code
for the main file, and a template for the cell, as well as <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#NMODL">NMODL</a> code for the channels. The NMODL files
will be compiled and a confirmation shown. If there is a problem, go to <strong>Settings -> General Properties</strong> and check location there for the NEURON home directory.
The contents of the *.mod and *.hoc files can be viewed by selecting the filename and pressing <strong>View</strong>.
</li>

<li>Click on <strong>Run Simulation</strong>. This should start NEURON and run the simulation you have just created.
</li>

<li>Back in neuroConstruct, once the simulation has finished, go to tab <strong>Visualisation</strong>, and click on <strong>Previous Simulations</strong>
You will see a list of all recorded simulations. Click on the simulation just completed and click <strong>Load Simulation</strong>.
The generated cell appears again. Press <strong>Replay</strong> to view the recorded simulation.
</li>


</ol>


<p>Have a look <a href="../Glossary_gen.html#3D View of Cells">here</a> to see the various options which can be set when viewing cells in 3D.</p>



<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
  </body>
</document>
